Finding Aid for Walter I. McKenzie Polar Bear Expedition papers, 1918-1945.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Walter I. McKenzie Polar Bear Expedition papers 1918-1945
McKenzie, Walter I. (Walter Ingles), 1888-1962.
19 folders and 1 oversize folder
Detroit attorney who served in 1918 and 1919 with the 339th U.S. Infantry during the American intervention in Archangel, Russia, the "Polar Bear Expedition." Selections from McKenzie's papers including correspondence, photographs, and other items relating to service in Polar Bear Expedition to northern Russia.
85307
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of the Walter McKenzie family (Donor no. 6495 ) and came to the library in 1980-1981. The diary and correspondence are photocopies. The originals are owned by Mrs. Margaret J. Midener, East Jordan, Mich. The Bentley borrowed the originals of the diary and correspondence for digitizing.
The collection is open for research.
Walter Ingles McKenzie was born in Muskegon, Michigan February 9, 1888. He graduated from the University of Michigan Law School in 1915. During World War I, he served as a member of the 339th Infantry sent to northern Russia as part of the Polar Bear Expedition; and during the 1920s and 1930s he was a Democratic party worker and candidate for state office.
In 1946, Walter McKenzie was granted a leave of absence from his position as Referee in Bankruptcy for the Eastern District of Michigan to serve as an Assistant U.S. Prosecutor at the International Military Tribunal for the Far East. As part of the so-called Japanese War Crimes Trial, McKenzie was specifically charged with that part of the indictment relating to Japanese military aggressions in Manchuria. McKenzie stayed in Tokyo for much of 1946, then returned to the United States in 1947, where he resumed the practice of law.
The Walter McKenzie Collection consists largely of materials created as a result of the Japanese War Crimes Trials. The collection has been arranged into eight series: Biographical/Personal; Correspondence; Articles, Speeches, etc.; International Military Tribunal for the Far East, International Prosecution Section; University of Michigan; World War I (Polar Bear Expedition); Miscellaneous; and Photographs. The Walter McKenzie Collection covers many aspects of McKenzie's life in addition to the Polar Bear expedition. The bulk of the collection consists largely of materials created as a result of the Japanese War Crimes Trials. The collection has been arranged into eight series: Biographical/Personal; Correspondence; Articles, Speeches, etc.; International Military Tribunal for the Far East, International Prosecution Section; University of Michigan; World War I (Polar Bear Expedition); Miscellaneous; and Photographs. Only the Polar Bear material and some biographical material has been digitized and can be viewed here. Researchers must visit the library to view the rest of McKenzie's collection. The Polar Bear materials consist of a diary, June 1918-July 1919, describing his voyage to Russia, his stay in a Red Cross Hospital there, routine work at headquarters, life in Archangel, a supply trip up the Dvina River in a gunboat in June 1919, and the voyage home. Also included are correspondence, June 1918-July 1919, describing life at Camp Custer, the voyage to Russia, life in Archangel, civilian conditions there, his ambition to go to the front, and his boat trip up the river. Other materials include ca. 30 picture postcards of Archangel, Murmansk, and countryside scenes, an issue of The Call, an English-language Bolshevik newspaper published in Moscow, a copy of the constitution of the Russian Socialist Federated Soviet Republic, an issue of The Mess Kit and one of the Daily Communique, both published in France for American soldiers, consisting of poems, and miscellaneous programs, clippings, and rosters.
Subjects:
McKenzie, Walter I. (Walter Ingles), 1888-1962.; Polar Bear Expedition.; Soviet Union--History--Allied Intervention, 1918-1920.; World War, 1914-1918.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Detroit (Mich.); McKenzie, Walter I. (Walter Ingles), 1888-1962.; Military art and science.; Polar Bear Expedition.; Soviet Union--History--Allied Intervention, 1918-1920.; Veterans of Foreign Wars of the United States
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- World War I (Polar Bear Expedition)
  - Introductory Materials, 4 items (Folder 1)
  - Diary of experiences in Russia, 1918-1919, 1 item, 127 pages (Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, January 1918-July 1919
    - January-June 1918, 7 items
    - July 1918, 30 items (Folder 4)
    - August-September, 1918 (Folder 5)
    - October-December 1918, 31 items (Folder 6)
    - January-March, 1919, 19 items (Folder 7)
    - April-May, 1919, 20 items (Folder 8)
    - June-July, 1919, 15 items (Folder 9)
  - Polar Bear Association Reunion Programs, 6 items (Folder 10)
  - Printed Material, 7 items (Folder 11)
    (Includes announcements of Polar Bear Association events)
  - Miscellaneous
    (Includes a copy of Vol. 1 No. 1 of The Mess Kit a humorous publication for "the Soldiers of the A.E.F."; an issue of The Call, a broadsheet of "the workers and peasants of Russia, to their English speaking fellow workers"; several issues of the Daily Communique; duty rosters; pamphlets; notes and personal items.)
    - [Bentley Library material], 22 items (Folder 12)
    - [Loaned Material], 17 items (Folder 13)
  - Newspaper clippings, 6 items (Folder 14)
  - Photocopies of other clippings, 41 items (Folder 15)
  - Post-cards of Russia, 33 items (Folder 16)
  - Polar Bear Photographs
    - Portraits of McKenzie, Draftees Marching, and Miscellaneous, 7 items (Folder 17)
    - Reunion group photos and Miscellaneous, 7 items (Folder 18)
    - Souvenir Folders: Life in the U.S. Army, Camp Mills, and New York City, Night Views (Folder 19)
      (Commercially produced packets of photos)
    - Group photos, 339th Infantry, Camp Devens, July 14, 1919 and Reunion photos, 1921-1945, 6 items; (outsize photos) (Folder 20)